ARGHYA CHATTERJEE



arghyame20buet@gmail.com

https://arghyachatterjee.github.io

A machine learning researcher experienced in applying deep learning, edge & cloud computing in computer vision, practical robotics & systems engineering application, and data-driven modern astronomy in order to serve the world, and encourage collaborative endeavor to explore outer world for better future of mankind.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Degree: BSc. in Mechanical Engineering Feb 2015 - Sept 2019

CGPA: 3.14/4.00

Khulna Public College, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: HSC in Science Jul 2012 - Aug 2014 *GPA*: 5.00/5.00 *Class Position*: 1st/60

• Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: SSC in Science Jan 2010 - May 2012 GPA: 5.00/5.00 Class Position: $1^{st}/60$

RESEARCH & PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant at Model & Project Lab, BUET

Software Team Advisor (& Ex. Lead) of Interplanetar for URC & ERC

Sep 2019 – Present

Supervisors: Dr. Md. Ashiqur Rahman and Mizanul H. Chowdhury

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Autonomous Navigation Based on GPS, SLAM, AR Tag and Object Detection for Safe

Exploration of Rovers on Rough Terrains, Caves and Mineral Ores of Earth and Mars.

Researcher & Collaborator

Undergraduate Thesis

Supervisors: Dr. Maglub Al Nur and Dr. Muhammad Abir

Topic: Computational Investigation on Pool Boiling IR Images for Segmentation of Dry Spots Automatically and Evaluating Performance of Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

Mar 2018 – Apr 2019

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

• Researcher & Team Leader

Undergraduate Project

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib

Topic: Fire and Flood Fighter Octocopter (UAV) for Extinguishing Fire in Fire Affected Buildings and Areas, and Distributing Flood Reliefs to people in Flood Affected Zones.

• Researcher & Technical Lead

Microsoft BD Internship Project

Supervisors: Sonia B. Kabir and Ashikur Rahman

Topic: Earlier Screening of Particular Disability in Children Through Mobile Application

Using Microsoft Products like Azure Cloud Platform and Bing Maps Server.

• Researcher & Team Leader

Undergraduate Project
Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam
Topic: Hand Wearable Solar Powered Obstacle Detection and Safe Navigation Device for Blind People in Low Cost.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

BUET Mars Rover Robotics Team

 Instructor at Model & Project Lab, BUET
 National Space Carnival & Camp
 Instructor & Academic Coordinator for Workshops & Camps

 Bangladesh Astronomical Society

 Instructor for Workshops & Seminars

 Beg 2019 - Present

 Dhaka, Bangladesh

 Dhaka, Bangladesh
 Dhaka, Bangladesh
 Dhaka, Bangladesh

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

• Bangladesh Astronomy Research Center Feb 2020 – Present Advisor & Member Dhaka, Bangladesh Activities: Give advice on research activities & how the organization should operate.

Youthprenuer Network (A Social Welfare Organization) Jun 2019 – Present Head of STEM Education & Development Dhaka, Bangladesh Activities: Instructed, Organized and Lead Projects, Workshops, Olympiads and Camps in Educational Institutions to Promote STEM Education in Bangladesh.

American Astronomical Society
 Country Co-Ordinator & Member
 Activities: Celebrated International Astronomical Events in Bangladesh in accordance with AAS, and Reported to Proper Authority for Publishing on their Monthly Magazines.

Bangladesh Astronomical Society Organizer & Member
Activities: Instructed and Organized Workshops, Quizzes and Seminars on Space and Astronomy to Promote Space Education among Future Generation of Bangladesh.

PUBLICATIONS

- A. Chatterjee, M. Galib and M. A. R. Sarkar, "Application of Arduino in designing modern electromechanical laboratory," 2017 IEEE International Conference on Power, Control, Signals and Instrumentation Engineering (ICPCSI), Chennai, 2017, pp. 222-225.
- A. Chatterjee, S. Dutta, P. Sarkar and A. B. M. A. A. Islam, "Obstacle Detector for Blind People with Low Cost (Poster Presentation)," *Proceedings of* 2017 International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS), Dhaka, 2017.

INTERNSHIPS & TRAININGS

Microsoft Bangladesh
 Internship Project: Disabling Disability through Microsoft Products

 Khulna Power Company Limited
 Training: Power Plant Visit & Industrial Attachment (3 weeks)

 Feb 2017 - May 2017
 Dhaka, Bangladesh
 Oct 2018 – Oct 2018
 Khulna, Bangladesh

SKILL SETS

- **Prg. Language:** Python, C++, C#, C, Arduino, Java, JavaScript, HTML, PHP, CSS, & LaTeX.
- Framework & OS: ROS, OpenCV, Nvidia Isaac SDK, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Caffe, Kubernetes, .NET, Django, WordPress, Linux, Mac & Windows.
- Software & Tool: Git & GitHub, Docker, MIPAR, SOLIDWORKS, AutoCAD, Ansys, PLC, Blender, Unity & UE 4, Verge3D, Kdenlive, Meshroom, Meshlab, OpenSpace, Google Earth Studio, Carla Simulator, Microsoft Airsim, OpenDroneMap & Microsoft Office Family.

- IDE, Compiler & Text Editor: CodeBlocks, Microsoft Visual Studio, MATLAB, Atom, Jupiter Notebook, PyCharm, Android Studio, Nodejs, IntelliJ IDEA, VS Code, Notepad++.
- Cloud Platform: AWS Compute, AWS RoboMaker & Storage, GCP, Google Colab.
- **Hardware:** GPS, LIDAR, 3D Stereo Camera, Nvidia Jetson Boards, Raspberry PI, PX4, Ardupilot, VESC, BLDC motor, Arduino & Nvidia AMD Boards with GTX & RTX Graphics.
- **Technology:** Computer Vision, Image Proc., Machine Learning, DCNN, DRL, Object Detection, Image Segmentation, SLAM, Photogrammetry, 3D Printing, AR, VR & MR, Game Dev, Web Dev, Video Editing, GPU, Edge & Cloud Computing.
- Language: Bangla, English & Hindi.
- Others: Astronomy, Creative Arts, Singing, Harmonium & Guitar Playing, Organizing, Show Hosting, Volunteering, Swimming, Cycling, Playing Cricket, Football & Badminton.

AWARDS, HONORS & SCHOLARSHIPS

 Gold Medalist from Duke of Edinburgh International Foundation 	Dec 2019
Awarded for Outstanding Extra-curricular & Service to the Society	London, UK
• 2 nd in Asia & 16 th Internationally in European Mars Rover Challenge	Sep 2019
European Space Foundation (ESF) & European Space Agency (ESA)	Kielce, PL
• Finalist in IEEE SS12 International Project Competition & Maker Fair	Jul 2017
SS12: Age of Innovation and Maker Fair 2017	Hyderabad, IN
• 1 st in National Project Show Competition (Senior Category)	May 2017
EEE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 3 rd in Inter University Project Show Competition	Apr 2017
Mechanical Festival, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 1 st in National Poster Presentation Competition	Mar 2017
Robolution, MIST	Dhaka, BD
• 2 nd in Inter University Project Show Competition	Nov 2016
CSE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 1 st in All Classes in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	2002-2014
Elizabeth Primary Sc., Khulna BKS Sc., Khulna Pub. Cl.	Khulna, BD
• Govt. Board Scholarship in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	y 2006-2014
Education Board of Bangladesh Govt., Jessore	Khulna, BD
Olympiad Achievements:	
• 1 st in Reg. R. of Science Olympiad'14 • 1 st in Reg. R. of Zoology Olympiad'14	
• 3 rd in Reg. & 10 th in Nat. R. of Astro-Olympiad'13 • 3 rd in Reg. R. of Math Olympiad'14	

CERTIFICATIONS

- **Deep Learning Specialization** (5 Course) by Deeplearning.ai on Coursera, Sept 2018.
- **Image and Video Processing:** From Mars to Hollywood with a Stop at the Hospital by Duke University on Coursera, Oct 2019.
- Intro to Satellite Communications by Institut Mines Télécom on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- **Wireless Communications for Everybody** by Yonsei University on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- **AstroTech:** The Science and Technology behind Astronomical Discovery by The University of Edinburgh on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- A Short Course on **Nuclear Power Engineering** by Institute of Nuclear Power Engineering, BUET, Apr 2018.

LEADERSHIPS

• **Head** of STEM Education & Development

Youthprenuer Network Team Interplanetar, BUET

• Software **Team Lead**

• **Technical Lead** of Internship Project

• **President** (Senior Rover Mate)

President

• **Team Lead** for Development & Planning

• **Founding** Member

• Country Co-Ordinator

• **Organizing** Secretary

Microsoft BD
BUET Rover Scout Group
Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET
ESAB, BUET Unit
Sceptre
American Astronomical Society
Nuclear Engineering Club, BUET

VOLUNTEERING

Sceptre (Poverty Alleviation Organization)

Activities: Org. free medical camps & distribute dress & sewing machines to poor people.

BUET Rover Scout Group

Activities: Volunteered on alumni day at BUET & org. flood relief distribution camp.

• Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School Scout Group
Activities: Volunteered on medical camps, tree plantation events & sports day at KBKSS.

WORKSHOPS & SEMINARS

- National Leadership Conference-2019 org. by WOC and English Olympiad.
- Youth Leadership Summit-2016 org. by Bangladesh Youth Leadership Centre.
- 4th BIRDS International Workshop on **Demystifying Satellites** org. by BRAC University.
- Seminar on **Zero Robotics** by M.H. Chowdhury of MIT org. by Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET.
- Seminar on **4-fold Resolution Increase in Endoscopic Imaging** by J.M. Kahn of Stanford University, org. by Dept. of Biomedical Eng., BUET.
- Workshop on **PCB**, **Graphic Designing** & **Technical Paper Writing** org. by IEEE BDS.
- Training on **AI for Beginners** & **Advanced AI with Python** org. by SBS Club, BUET.
- Workshops on **CFD**, **Ansys Fluent**, **Solidworks & 3D Printing** org. by Involute Tech BD.

MEMBERSHIPS

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (**IEEE**)
- American Society of Mechanical Engineers (**ASME**)
- American Astronomical Society (AAS)
- American Physical Society (APS)
- American Nuclear Society (ANS)
- Bangladesh Astronomical Society (BAS)
- Bangladesh Youth Leadership Centre Graduate Network (BGN)
- Engineering Students Association of Bangladesh (**ESAB**)

REFERENCES

Dr. M. A. Rashid Sarkar

Academic Advisor Ex. Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Professor, Dept. of Nuclear Eng., MIST. Email: rashid@me.buet.ac.bd

Dr. Maglub Al Nur

Thesis Supervisor Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Email: maglub@me.buet.ac.bd • Dr. Muhammad Abir

Thesis Co-Supervisor Ex. Post Doc. R. Associate, Dept. of NSE, MIT. Imaging Specialist, Phoenix Nuclear Labs. Email: miabir@mit.edu

Mizanul H. Chowdhury

Project Co-Supervisor Arch. & Admin of ZR, Space Systems Lab, MIT. Email: mizanul@mit.edu